this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine
online at computer.org software
developers are you ready it's time to
upgrade your data platform to inner
systems iris
choose your language choose your tools
choose your environment
collaborate build faster and deploy more
efficiently
when you can make faster decisions
there's no telling what you'll create
ready set code start coding for free
visit intersystems.com try to try iris
hello this is justin baier for software
engineering radio and today i'm speaking
with adam shostak
adam's a leading expert on threat
modeling and a consultant entrepreneur
technologist
author and game designer he's a member
of the black cat review board and helped
create the cve and many other things
he currently helps many organizations
improve their security via showstack and
associates
and advises startups including as a
mach37 star mentor
wallet microsoft teacher of the auto run
fix into windows update
was the lead designer of the sdl threat
modeling tool version 3
and created the elevation of privilege
game adam is the author of threat
modeling designing for security and the
co-author of the new school
of information of security hi adam and
welcome to the show hey
great to be here so adam just to start
off the show before we delve into what
threat modeling is
can you define what a threat is in this
context
sure the definition of threat that i
like to use
is it's a promise of future harm right
i'm going to hit you i'm
going to attack your system and so a
threat
is something that might happen and
oftentimes a threat
is accompanied by a condition that
that you can avoid the threat i'm gonna
hit you if you don't give me your lunch
money
okay so essentially the threat is almost
the impending doom
and there's a likelihood that it's gonna
happen at some point and there's some
negative consequence as a result of that
and importantly something you can do to
avoid it
okay so i can implement mitigations so
is that where threat modeling fits in
exactly okay so when we discuss that
what
is threat modeling overall what's the
goal of it and what is it doing to
achieve those
if you build something without thinking
about security
your security team might show up and say
oh my gosh you've got all these
problems we can't ship and that's an
awful situation for everyone
you're annoyed you were planning to ship
these awesome new features
security is annoyed they didn't have a
chance to influence the design
threat modeling is a way for security
and engineering
to collaborate and think through
the threats that are going to apply to
the system
ideally before you've written a line of
code okay so the idea is essentially
catch the threats before they happen
have a plan to solve the threats before
they happen and
try to avoid the threats happening when
you actually ship the product to
customers
exactly so why would we want to do that
instead of
applying the threat modeling after we've
already built the product what's the
downside to doing it at the end well the
downside to doing it at the end
is as i'm sure your listeners know
the cheapest time to make changes to
code
is before the code is written the
easiest way to fix a bug
is to not introduce the bug or to catch
it super early
the later the code the later you are
making
changes to the code the more expensive
they become there are dependencies on
the way things are happening
and so every change has repercussions
it has knock-on effects it has ripple
effects
and so doing this work early gives you
insight into how to avoid that rework
but i do want to talk about one time
when it makes sense
to do it late right after an acquisition
if you're starting out today it can make
sense to do a threat model
of what you've already built because
you've got to start somewhere you can
also start by threat modeling just the
new features
and thinking about some security desk
realizing that you're going to have to
come back
take a look at the big picture but you
can start small
if you're starting today and you should
okay so essentially
you don't want to have to do it at the
end but if you're forced because you're
acquiring a new product you've never had
it before and
the previous company has ever done a
threat model it's better to have
something rather than nothing because
then at least you have a
plan that you can start working on to
fix the product yes
fantastic so then just kind of changing
direction a little bit
i know you've kind of covered this but i
just want to explicitly discuss
how does threat modeling actually
benefit my overall organization
or the projects that i'm working on so
the first way it benefits your
organization
is by giving you a structured systematic
and comprehensive approach
to security if we're going to create a
model of the entire thing that we're
shipping
it gives us an opportunity to do
analysis of the whole
right so we can be systematic we can be
structured using techniques
and we'll talk about these in a little
bit i think stride or a kill
chain to think through what's going on
you know a lot of people when they start
out with threat modeling
will just ask what can go wrong we can
put some structure on that
and by applying a structure to a model
of the system as a whole
we can get to assurance that we're
actually being comprehensive
so at a technical level we have this
assurance that what we're doing
is structured systematic and
comprehensive
then at an organizational level the
benefit that we get
is collaboration instead of conflict
between
teams and that is a super important
benefit
that we often overlook that this
conflict exists
because look if you're not threat
modeling
and i as an engineer come to my security
team
and i say so what should i do to secure
the thing that we're building
i'm going to get advice like software
composition analysis
and static analysis and penetration
testing and fuzzing
all of which are great techniques to use
and
all of which happen later in the design
and development of the product
and development of the process
security doesn't have a seat at the
table
and so design choices that you're making
get encoded
they get encoded in the apis they get
encoded
in the distribution of components
and they become hard to change so threat
modeling
diffuses conflict which is a massive
organizational benefit
okay so by having a structured process
we ensure consistency
and that we're covering all the things
that we should be covering whereas these
technical
processes like static analysis or
fuzzing are going to miss things
and by also doing this at an
organizational level early on
as a collaborative effort we're able to
work as a security and development group
and resolve the issues before we build
that issue with the model
or in a threat into the product
that then is built in and is very
expensive to change
after the fact so knowing all of that
is there any benefit on the compliance
side so if i'm building a product that
has to be
hipaa compliant or it has to be pci
compliant or any other
number of standards how does threat
modeling help on that front is there
something that i can then produce to my
customers and say
hey look my product is compliant and
here's how we achieve the compliance
the largest compliance benefit that you
get from threat modeling
isn't always customer visible a lot of
compliance requirements
are difficult for engineers to
understand
why do i have to do all of this stuff
the reason you do that
stuff is because there are threats to
the system
a lot of systems to which you need to
comply jump
over the threat step there's an implicit
threat model
and say here's a control here's a
control here's a control
when you go through the threat modeling
process you do two things
one you make explicit the reason
for the control and you can make a
decision about
is the control in the compliance guide
the best control
or is there an alternative control that
makes more sense
and oftentimes you end up with less work
and a more secure system because instead
of applying controls
where there's no threat but it might be
a threat to another version of the
system or an implicit
idea that if you implemented it this way
you'd need this control
and let me be explicit here rather than
really modeling and meta modeling
a lot of compliance guidance says you
need antivirus software
the antivirus software is there to
prevent malicious software from getting
onto the system
with today's devops world we often do
things like
immutable builds or phoenix builds
those also control the threat of malware
getting onto the system
because if it's an immutable build the
malware can't write itself to disk
at that point you're addressing the
concern
you're addressing the need that the
anti-malware requirement
addresses and you can make a solid case
that this control i'm putting in place
well it's not the one listed in the
standard is an effective mitigation of
the threat
and therefore we are compliant and you
are compliant
and we get these other benefits from the
architecture
and so compliance can get a massive
win from thinking through the threats
that are present
and addressing them more rationally okay
so the anti-virus
solution essentially isn't necessary
because of how i'm implementing it and
my threat model would detect that
that control is no longer necessary
almost as if i'm using
docker containers to deploy on my
software and my docker containers are
destroyed every
30 minutes why do i need to put
antivirus on there because no files will
ever persist for more than 30 minutes so
the likelihood that malware is going to
execute in that time is
slim to none and even if it does execute
it's gone in 15 minutes on average
exactly so essentially by having the
threat model i can then say to the
compliance people
yeah i know the standard says you want
me to have
antivirus on every single server that
gets stood up or every single
application
server that's running but there's no
need and here's why and here's our
threat model that says
this doesn't make sense so kind of
shifting gears just a little bit
what kinds of projects benefit from
threat modeling is there like a certain
size a certain type like if i'm building
a software as a service a cloud-based
application
and ai machine learning blockchain
system
which ones benefit i think the ones that
include technology
so pretty much every application should
benefit from some level of threat
modeling
in indeed and some of these some threat
modeling has been done right your
blockchain projects
tend to have a threat model either
explicitly or
implicitly with them that tell you
hey if you're implementing a blockchain
thing
you need to worry about the security of
the client
because if i can steal your private if i
can break in
steal your private keys i'm stealing
real money
right and so some of these threats have
been worked through
similarly with machine learning
microsoft has published
a guide to threat modeling with machine
learning
there's a group called the berryville
institute of machine learning that's
also published a threat model guide
where a lot of the analysis
has been done relative to an abstracted
system
and that means that if i'm building a
system that involves machine learning
i can start by reading through
one or the other or even both of these
guides
and saying how does this threat apply to
the system
i'm working on and for a lot of systems
that will be sufficient now maybe what
you're doing
is threat modeling to identify cats in
pictures on the internet
and the downside to that system
misidentifying a
mug of tea as a cat are pretty low
or maybe what you're doing is you're
doing machine learning
in the news right now to decide
whether or not people will be taken
aside for additional screening at the
airports
i would hope in that second situation
where the impact of a bad decision is
higher
they're going to do more extensive
threat modeling
exactly we had done a previous episode
on some machine learning security
and as you kind of mentioned that whole
based on what you're modeling your
threat model needs to be kicked up a
notch depending on the negative impacts
of using that
but just to circle back a little bit you
said implicit versus an
explicit threat model can you just
define those sure
an explicit threat model is one
where you have written down
what you've done and why you've done it
and and in fact maybe this is a good
time for me to step back
and talk about the structure of threat
modeling a little bit
and say i believe that threat modeling
involves answering
four key questions what are we working
on
what can go wrong what are we going to
do about it and did we do a good job
so what are we working on do we have an
explicit written
scope for our threat model
what can go wrong have we written down
the answers
and importantly how we got to the
answers what are we going to do about it
you know what mitigations are we going
to put in place what risks are we
accepting and why
and then did we do a good job retrospect
analyze what we did
say did we get about the right number of
threats out of this
do people feel that the process was
effective and so
the explicit threat model is the answers
to those questions
the implicit model is someone
someone was told to go think about it
they did
and they said yeah we're good or no i
need
i think we need to address these four
threats how did you get to those four
threats well they're important threats i
i thought about the system
and this is what's come out so almost
the explicit is we went through an
exercise we almost ran a project
and created a project and said here's
our scope this is the questions we need
answered as
at the end of this project this is our
written report that needs to come out of
this
and this is the feedback that we're
going to circle back for the next time
we have to do this
whereas the implicit is almost i read
the owasp top 10
and we have a web app and we do sql so
sql injection is important
make sure we don't have sql injections
on our web page yes
and you make it sound so waterfally let
let me talk about this in the agile
world because i think that's important
in today's
for a great many people working today
if i have a big diagram on my wall of
what we're working on
and i go up to it and i say you know
this let's let's pretend we're working
on a system like
itunes i'm gonna update the
recommendation
engine i've done a spike i've tested the
new recommendation engine i believe we
can put it in and my goal
for this next two weeks is to get that
recommendation into production
there's no new data flows nothing is
changing the way it crosses the trust
boundary
so i don't think there are any threats
relative to this work
that's an explicit bit of threat
modeling done with the team
it doesn't produce a written report as
you said someone else comes up and says
this week i'm adding support for artists
to upload
wav files as a new form that we're going
to ship music in
okay so i've got a new file type
it's coming from you know
we bound who can be an artist on itunes
but it's a pretty low bar
so we assume that attackers will use
this
so i'm really going to worry about the
parser here i'm going to worry about
elevation of privileged threats that
come
with those files and in fact this entire
two weeks
i'm going to work through the best
secure design of the purser
because we know that this is problematic
and
out of what i just said we get some
kanban board items
we get some written analysis records
because
the very simple act of saying what are
we working on
a new path for files to come in from the
outside
produced awareness that those that
threats could accompany those files and
therefore we needed to do deeper
analysis so we can be very agile
in doing this while still being explicit
and lightweight for the things that are
appropriately
lightweight and more in depth where we
need to be
okay so i actually want to touch a
little more on how we can
take and track threats as a result of
our threat modeling process in the agile
overall software development and even
waterfall and touch on that a little bit
later
but i want to circle a little earlier
back in your explanation
can we talk about what a data flow and
what a trust boundary are
sure so one way to threat model
is to use data flow diagrams to answer
the question of what can go wrong
and data flow diagrams dfds
are commonly associated with threat
modeling because threats tend to follow
the data flows
a data flow diagram is a really simple
way of expressing what we're working on
it has roughly five components
it has processes which are all running
code
it has data flows it has data stores
it has external actors and it has trust
boundaries
and trust boundaries are the are the
unusual piece here they're what you
don't usually draw on the whiteboard
and a trust boundary is anywhere
different principles
interact anywhere entities that have
different permissions
different rights different authority
interact
on opposite sides of a trust boundary
and so we make those explicit
we draw them as dotted lines so let's
delve a little more into the trust
boundary subject though okay so we're
kind of discussing there's external
actors and you're drawing these trust
boundaries and
what does that really mean is that you
know on one half it's untrusted the
other half it's trusted kind of like a
firewall
is it a little more ephemeral or vague
it's not vague a trust boundary needs to
exist and it needs to be enforced a
firewall is a great way to enforce a
trust boundary
so are user ids if i have a traditional
linux system that has
root and it has atom and it has justin
and it has
alice as users on the system
i can't read your files you can't read
alice's unless she's
chamodded them so there's a trust
boundary that exists between
us and there's an enforcement mechanism
if i've got a web browser talking to a
database backend
maybe i have ldap implemented so that
the sql user on the web server is the
same as the sql user on the database
or maybe they operate in different
organizational domains but there's a
trust boundary that exists between those
two systems the web server
and the database and we need an
authentication mechanism to ensure that
one talking to the other
knows who's on each side of that
boundary
okay and just for our listeners who
aren't super familiar with linux chamod
is
related to changing the permissions on a
file saying
you know justin could then read the file
but going a little more down this rabbit
hole of
trust boundaries how do i actually find
them in my diagram is there like a
secret trick to finding them
or is it just there's an external user
and an internal system
and i don't want to allow the external
user to do whatever they want so there
must be a trust boundary between them
so that's a great place to start and the
trick to finding them
is saying is there any control
or could we put a control between here
and there
so as you're looking at say
a web server the web server
has a set of
code that runs inside the web server
there's not really a way to put a
boundary between that code
and the web server when it's running
the web server might depend on files on
disk
so i might run the web server as
user atom and make sure that the files
are all owned by justin
and are read only relative to everyone
but justin
that way the web server if someone
breaks into it
can't write to those files so there's a
trust boundary there
it's a trust boundary again that's
enforced by the
user id system by the linux kernel
and you can go through and say could we
put a control there
and if you can then there's a trust
boundary that exists
and today that trust boundary might or
might not be enforced
right it might be that all of the files
the
web server runs as adam all of the files
are owned by adam
so there's no trust boundary present or
there's
there's no trust boundary that's
enforced but we could install one
if we want to add that layer of defense
so almost the unenforced trust boundary
is the
there's one in my head and i think that
there's a separation but it might not
actually be there or at least i think
there should be a separation
well that's a great question you know
here's here's the thing that happens
is you think that trust boundary exists
and i don't and so i write my code
such that the web server writes to
configuration files say
you don't think it's there and so you
write all of your configuration to the
sql database
now we've got a half enforced trust
boundary
right so all the work that you're doing
to put your configuration in a safe
place
is undercut by the work that i'm doing
when we threat model for the first time
by making it explicit even if we're
making it very lightweight explicit on a
whiteboard
we identify these different mental
models that people
had and we discover hey we could make
improvements here would be way cheaper
if i had written my code the same way
you did the first time around
and threat modeling helps us do that
okay so by having that almost
explicit threat modeling we're not
introducing vulnerabilities by having
assumptions that are undocumented
and unproven so changing gears a little
bit
let's discuss specifically how we
approach threat modeling
so you discussed in your book the
attacker-centric
the asset-centric and the
software-centric approaches can you
discuss what each of these
are and some of the advantages and
disadvantages for them
sure and let me start by saying we're
gonna end with software
which is what you should be doing and
i'll explain why
so attacker-centric modeling is
we're going to build personas for the
people who are going to attack
us and use it to understand how they're
going to attack and what they might do
and that's difficult because if you go
and talk to usability experts the way to
build
personas is to go and engage with
the persona in their natural environment
to understand what they do and why you
can't go
and talk to ransomware authors as
they're doing this
their work you can't go and talk to
spies as they're doing this work
and so it's hard to create good personas
it's hard to create a complete list of
personas
and so this approach is expensive and it
often leads us astray
similarly asset centric threat modeling
what do attackers
want what's the valuable pieces here
can lead you to miss things you can be
thinking about
oh this is a list of expired passwords
that we don't care about because they're
expired we're keeping them around so
people can't change their password back
to this
those are super valuable to attackers
who want to use the password
you know justin at ieee.org
on some other website to see if they can
log in as you because you haven't
changed your password
and so asset centric approaches tend to
lead us to miss
things they tend to lead us to things
which are out of scope
oh i'm just doing a banking web app
but the money is really in the general
ledger so i'm going to focus on that
no we want to focus on what we're
working on
and what we're working on is the
software the technology
it's the thing that we as engineers know
best it's the thing that we ought to be
able to talk about
and that's why we start from that when i
go and i talk to engineers
and i say what are we working on here
people will jump up at the whiteboard
and start drawing pictures
i like to start the threat modeling work
from that natural starting point of what
people know
what they're comfortable talking about
and what we can scope
and understand okay so essentially
the attacker-centric is all about who's
actually going to attack us
and that's almost impossible because
that requires you
traveling to nigeria to speak to whoever
the nigerian princes that's writing the
fishing
emails asset centric
doesn't really work so well because it's
all surrounding the crown jewels and
what you might think is
the most valuable thing in the world
might not actually be what the attackers
are going to go after first they're
going to go after
the low-hanging fruit and then work
their way to your crown jewels
and software centric is all around what
am i
actually building i'm building a banking
web app it's all around money it's all
around transactions
i need to secure this from the outside
in
not just the one database where i have
the balances for everybody's accounts
yes
and also crucially it's the thing that's
inside your control right it's the thing
that threat modeling can affect when you
do it
okay so essentially because i actually
control what the software is going to do
how it's going to be architected how
it'll be deployed
i can actually manage that risk
versus attacker-centric i can't control
who attacks my application i can't say
well
we're only going to allow nation-states
to attack this not the script kitty
[Laughter]
it would be great if they are paid to
keep out signs
calling all developers there's no
telling what you can create when you
upgrade your data platform to
intersystems iris
are you ready to build the applications
you want however you want them
are you ready to develop applications
faster than ever collaborate
build faster and deploy more efficiently
tomorrow's next breakthroughs are
waiting for you today
enter systems iris data platform ready
set code start coding for free
visit intersystems.com try to try iris
so let's just move off the topic of the
different approaches to threat modeling
and move more into how we're going to
find the threats in a model
so i'm actually going to be linking in
an article from software engineering
institute on 12 different methods for
threat modeling
but i wanted to get your opinion why are
there so many different methods
to find threats in a model why are there
so many different programming languages
right different different methods have
different strengths and weaknesses
and as we've developed
understanding of how to do things we've
also developed
new tools to to help us threat model
and so in the same way that it is
somewhat unusual today to see code being
written in perl
it is somewhat unusual to see some of
the methods listed in that paper
in active use because we've learned
as we've gone through the experience of
using them
and let me make this concrete so for
example attack trees are one of the
oldest methods to structure your
analysis
and it turns out that really building an
attack tree
is more structured than just
brainstorming and thinking about what
can go wrong
willy-nilly but there's not a lot of
guidance it's a
the guidance says things like think
about
other ways for this to happen
okay but if i'm not a security
expert how do i know that i actually
have this
done well and so attack trees
seem like a good idea
and then in practice you try and use
them
and they can be they don't offer the
same support and structure that newer
methods offer
so you mentioned newer methods what
would you consider would be newer
methods to threat modeling
so i think the newest method would be
the use of a kill chain to ask what
could go wrong
and kill chains come
from the idea that
an attacker has to follow a set of steps
in order to
break in successfully they might
do some reconnaissance they might take
an exploit
and weaponize it that that is to say
package
the exploit against a vulnerability into
an attractive looking
email with an attachment the user clicks
on that
and the exploit runs the exploit
takes control of the system and it does
an
installation step then it tries to
persist itself
and only then does the attacker have
control
and are able to execute their initial
goal
and by going through and thinking about
each of those steps
relative to what are we working on i can
say what are the best delivery points
here
if a piece of software installed itself
how would it do that
we talked about immutable builds in
phoenix builds
database versus configuration files and
so you can see
that those possibilities get illuminated
by the kill chain
and so we can use the kill chain to
structure the way we answer
what can go wrong yes so i know in the
cyber security space we discuss a lot
the lockheed martin kill chain which is
i think kind of what you're referring to
it is i didn't want to go all geeky
about the detail and history of the kill
chain
so almost what you're saying is so that
kill chain i would
say oh my application accepts file
uploads that would be a great thing to
weaponize from an attacker perspective
to execute files on my system
exactly okay and then moving over a
little bit
i know that you mainly worked with
stride
in your previous uh work can you
discuss a little bit what stride is what
it stands for and how to use it
sure so stride is the first
really structured approach to threat
modeling it's a model of what can go
wrong
it stands for spoofing tampering
repudiation
which is to say denying that something
happened or that you're not responsible
for it
information disclosure denial of service
and elevation of privilege
and so you can use stride as a checklist
as you think through each piece
of your diagram each piece of software
you're working on
you could say how could someone spoof
themselves to this pretend to be someone
else
how could someone tamper with it or
modify it without my authorization
etc etc and so you can
use stride as
a structured analytic technique and it's
actually the first
really the first of what i think of as
the structured analytic
techniques and you know you mentioned
that
i i've talked a lot about stride over
the years it's true let me credit here
the authors
lauren karnfelder and prairie garg
and say that they really opened my eyes
to the possibility of structuring our
work and
for a long time i confused that
possibility
with the way to achieve it and
as time has gone by i've really seen
that we can
alternate structures that we can use
stride or the kill chain
or something else we could use an attack
tree
to structure our thinking and we can
interchange
componentry right in the same way that i
started answering this question by
talking about multiple programming
languages we can use different tools
to achieve the same goal and that's
incredibly important as we think about
how do we engage with threat modeling
as a discipline as a research topic
and as an opportunity to make more
secure systems
so threat modeling is almost an overall
concept that you can take these
different tools and
plug them in and by swapping out
different pieces and putting in
different tools
we can actually get different outcomes
and benefits and discoveries of new
things that we wouldn't have detected
i.e we might have used stride before and
then we used kill chain and all of a
sudden we detected that there was
something we didn't even think about
with stride
absolutely and it's a trap to say
threat modeling is or the way the threat
model is
you can say the way we should threat
model this particular thing
today is this but we have
we have a toolbox and we need to
conceive of threat modeling
as a toolbox not as a a single way of
doing things
so what actually affects the usefulness
of this these different methods
do you focus in on someone's experience
threat modeling what kinds of diagrams
you have for the software what kind of
software or application it is whether
it's cloud-based on-prem
a software as a service a kernel
all of this all all of the context in
which the work
is done influences how we do the work
so for example if i'm threat modeling a
mobile app
maybe a state machine is more useful
than a data flow diagram right my data
flow diagram
is the mobile app top talks to the bank
and hopefully not but probably it talks
to a bunch of advertising servers and
tracking services etc
and the questions that i'm going to ask
are all
what are the state transitions how do i
move from not logged in to logged in
how do i move from the see my balance
screen
to the transfer money screen and do i
need
a secondary authentication there in some
way
and so in that case what we're working
on
influences the form in which we think
about what we're working on from a data
flow diagram
to a state machine to swim lanes and
message flow diagrams
and similarly we can pick and choose
between the tools
for what can go wrong okay so i imagine
after we go through all these
different threat modeling methods and
maybe we pick
three of them and generate a whole big
giant list of threats
how do i actually filter this down to
say these are the threats that i need to
care about
so there's a couple of things that you
can do
the first is easy fixes first right
fix your s3 buckets please fix the
fix your cloud data stores we don't need
to do
a should we worry about an exercise on
that
the time we need to do the exercise of
should we worry about this or should we
take action on this
is only once we know that the fixes are
complicated that this would be hard to
fix
now but also we need to put this
knowledge into our backlog
we need to document the knowledge and
this is closer to standard software
engineering
than it is to threat modeling and so
it's a boundary step in a sense
where we learned that this stuff can go
wrong
i've got a bunch of things that are easy
to make changes to i'm going to put
those in
and i'm going to treat the rest as part
of my backlog
and one of the things that people often
say and this might be a good time to
bring
it up is what's the relationship between
risk
and threat modeling and to me threat
modeling
is where we find the things on which we
can do the risk analysis
later and sometimes that risk analysis
is important and sometimes it's it's
just
easier to take action okay so
essentially don't just discount
something because you think it's
ridiculous
i'm a small bank and i don't think that
china's going to try to
hack into my mobile app that only has
five users
while that might be realistic from a
risk perspective that your risk of a
nation-state attacker using
certain exploits against your system
that you're not going to be able to
defend against
is minimal you shouldn't just throw it
away and pretend like it doesn't exist
yes right if you're going to let's say
you are a bank
you have a risk register you have a list
and whenever we deal with risk there are
four steps we can take
we can accept risk we can transfer it we
can mitigate it and we can eliminate it
and mature risk management does not
involve the developer saying
i don't know what to do about a
nation-state so i'm going to ignore it
ignore was not on my list of four
right except was and maybe accept as a
reasonable thing
and then we want to say who can accept
the risk
how is that tracked how much risk have
they accepted
and is that risk appropriate for their
seniority within the organization for
the organization as a whole
so for example a junior developer
probably shouldn't be accepting a risk
that
others a sql injection that might dump
our whole customer database
whereas the ceo accepting that risk is
completely different
yes exactly and so this is why it goes
into the backlog
and this gets to we talked earlier
about we need to write it down we need
to have a record that we did this
work and so a lot of times this stuff
can be tracked
in standard bugs right the the risks to
my software system
you know maybe if it's a security one
severity item
only a vp can close that bug and the vp
has to log into jira
and close the bug and say i accept this
risk
and there's a technique that i've become
really fond of which is bug bars
that encapsulate what the severity is
who's allowed to make decisions about it
and
that's much more and the only thing we
think about
is what is the impact of this bug and it
simplifies the whole discussion a lot of
times we get into these very convoluted
arguments we get into these systems
where we try and put
numbers on these things which are unique
to threat modeling
when really they need to be processed
with all of the other risks right what
is the risk
that my database will leak versus what
you know as we're recording this on
march 20th i hope you don't mind me
saying that
we have the covid virus there's a lot of
questions what does this mean to my
organization can i get work done
maybe today the risk that someone will
steal our database
is acceptable relative to the risk that
our customers can't log in
but boy next week i want to come back to
that risk and we want to make those
decisions
in the way that's right for our
organizations exactly so
essentially treat these threats that
we're finding
as bugs and assign some level of risk to
them
and track them in your bug tracking
system that way your developers are kept
in the loop on what's expected of them
it's all done in the same place your
projects are managed in that same system
however you approach that management and
then by having
that risk awareness and that
understanding that
you know maybe while my whole workforce
is remote giving everyone vpn is okay
but six months from now when they're all
back on site
maybe everyone doesn't need to have vpn
access
that we might want to revisit all of
these books
yes absolutely so just changing gears a
little bit here
i want to discuss privacy and threat
modeling
so i know that's been a hot topic
recently
how can i leverage threat modeling to
discover possible privacy issues
so there are a number of collections of
privacy threats that we can think about
the one that i see under the most active
development
is called linden and
i'm not going to attempt to rattle off
what linden stands for
but it's a very privacy-centric
collection
there are other collections which are
and lyndon is focused on things like
unobservability
and unlinkability and these are
privacy-centric topics
where we avoid linkability between
entities
because then all sorts of harms can't
come to pass
there are other approaches like looking
at dan solov's list of harms
which are much more outcome focused
and shoes and again every time you
threat model
it's what are the tools i'm pulling from
my toolbox
as you develop a more mature privacy
practice and a lot of companies are
getting here now
because of gdpr because of ccpa
there's a list of problems that you want
to avoid
you can treat that not as a compliance
exercise but as an engineering exercise
how do we avoid this negative outcome
how do we address the need for
forgettability
or data access and integrate that
into your development process so that
you're
achieving these goals in a balanced way
with all of the other things which you
need to do to have a successful
product treating it as something that
you
bolt on at the end leads to more
expensive
more difficult decisions than if you
think about it up front
okay and just for our listeners linden
stands for linkability identifiability
non-repudiation detectability disclosure
of
information content on awareness policy
and consent non-compliance i will
definitely put a link in the show notes
for that because
that is a mouthful but just kind of
delving a little more into what you said
so
should i actually track these privacy
threats that i'm detecting as part of
my threat modeling process with my
security threats should i do it the
exact same way
is there a special way i should be doing
it that's different should these not go
in my bug tracker
you know i think every time we add
a this is special and different
we increase the risk that people will
get confused
we increase the training requirements we
increase
the task switching requirement
i think all of those are negative and as
we think about
what engineering processes ought to be
like
those are things we want to avoid and
these are things that other parts of the
company often cares about
and so what is the right balance for
your organization
you know when i worked at microsoft
we had pretty technically savvy lawyers
telling a lawyer that they should look
at a at a bug database
not gonna say that was reasonable
unexpected
but it wouldn't have
been like having three arms right
it it would be something that i think i
could have discussed and i go to a lot
of i work with a lot of clients in a lot
of different places
and the idea that a lawyer would use the
bug tracker and look at things
is inconceivable exactly so essentially
you need to
articulate it and present it in a format
that the people that it care
that care about these privacy issues are
able to understand it so
lawyers who are worried about your legal
compliance with a privacy regulation
need to be able to understand yes these
are the privacy threats we've seen
this is how we're addressing them in a
maybe not necessarily technical manner
but a way that they could go into the
courtroom and argue
we're doing something about this we
promise yep
and maybe that's i have a project
manager crafter report for them once a
week
maybe maybe it's a different process but
it's
it depends on your organization
the way you answer the question what can
go wrong
what are we going to do about it and
making that
as lightweight as you can right
more energy on the doing the analysis
the fixing than on the documentation
we don't want documentation is there to
serve a purpose
the agile world loves the phrase you
ain't gonna need it
so let's apply that to threat modeling
and create only the things we need
ask for what we really need rather than
oh we need a report like this or a
report like that
because adam talked about in his book
please don't please don't ever say that
exactly so only worry about what you
actually are going to need as a demand
is put in place for it
so let's just dive a little more in on
that risk management discussion we were
having earlier
a follow-up do you recommend doing a
formal risk management
with like a quantitative or a
qualitative technique or more of an
ad hoc risk management i think you had
kind of touched on that answer before
but i just wanted to dive into it and
make it explicit
yes as is not your lawyer
i'm i'm not here to advise on
risk per se the
the approach that i find to be most
aligned with
engineering at most organizations i work
with
are bug bars where we say
this severity of impact
leads to this level of person making a
decision about this
because the the ability to think about
risk
is usually correlated with seniority
right the vp of engineering or the ceo
makes a decision about all about all the
banks data going out
we as engineers don't make that
call and when we conflate
threats and risks which is really easy
using english as an informal
unstructured language it's easy to go
back and forth and i caught myself doing
it once earlier in this
in this podcast but thinking about
threat modeling as an engineering
discipline that's designed to produce
problems to be addressed is
what i see leading to the most success
okay so and diving in a little earlier
you mentioned the four ways to actually
manage your threats mitigate accept
transfer how do i track these threats
that i'm accepting
and how do i communicate them to the
customer
so actually it's funny that you said it
that way i don't know if this was
intentional but you said threats and i
said risk
it's classic risk management to accept
mitigate
transfer or eliminate and
what you need to do is to have some form
of communications
to the customer saying we expect you to
make a decision about this
so for example opening files can be
risky
so we warn people and then they get used
to those warnings and they fail to even
see that they're there
the java license historically has said
you may not use
java in nuclear power plant control
right so that's one way to say that is
you put it in the license
another way to do this is to write a
deployment guide or a security guide
for your customers that says hey
if you're deploying our product we
expect
that it will be behind a firewall i was
talking to
some people who make very very big
lab equipment sort of lab equipment that
sells for a million bucks or so
and this lab equipment has i don't have
a number to call it 50 pcs
incorporated into it in various ways
and then it has a gateway that's
actually built into it
and their deployment manual says we have
a lot of old crafty technology
in the guts of this thing i don't think
those are the precise words but that's
what it says
do not enable ip routing between
this the innards of this system and
anything
else you will hurt yourself and i think
that's a perfectly
reasonable outcome of a threat model
right those 50 pcs that are doing data
acquisition
some of them have some very low level
code that's written to pull data off of
serial ports
very very quickly and
it's harder and harder to write that
code on a modern operating system
because the operating system say no you
can't sit in the kernel and do that no
one needs to do that
and so some of these systems are old and
outdated but they put that into a
security ops guide which is a way
to loop back to your question is a way
to tell the customer
this is what we expect this is what we
learned throughout modeling
formally or informally right in the in
the case of those old pcs
they knew about that problem they didn't
need to write a threat model to get
there
but the output of your strat model
sometimes does go to the customer
and say do this not that okay so i think
traditionally
in almost the pci retail realm
you have a point of sale application and
as part of
that there's a deployment guide that
says this is how you deploy this to be
pci dss compliant and
here are all the threats that we
identified and these are all the
switches that you need to flip
if you don't want to have a really bad
day with your point of sale system and
fail all your
audits so that's the same almost as your
discussion of communicating with the
customer we have this old technology
built into our system we can't change it
please don't put it on the internet it's
going to end very very badly for you
exactly so switching gears a little bit
what if we choose to mitigate that risk
how should i actually test my software
to make sure
it really is mitigated so when we say
mitigate
what we really mean is
to install controls right i'm going to
make the operating system immutable and
i am taking a dependency on that
so there what we want to do is we want
to write tests
we want to see can i write a file
can i change the configuration of
immutability
from userland what happens
if i attempt to write a file and if i
have a test right this is a standard
test driven development
unit testing if i have a test that tries
to write a file
and then four lines later in that test
code it tries to read from that file
and if it ever succeeds it pops a 7-1
bug and breaks the build
then that's good maybe what i want is
operational controls i don't want to run
that as a test
in my build pipeline i want to write it
as almost like an assertion
whereas if the assertion is ever
violated
i said fault i have an operational test
that attempts to write a file every
three minutes
right put in a cron job or something
and if the cron job ever succeeds
i know that there's an operational
problem and i should image that machine
right now and take it out of the pool of
active servers
and so this is very similar to the test
work that people are doing in agile
shops
today fellow that i worked with at
microsoft
said threat modeling is just test
planning and test design
and well i think that's a little bit
extreme
there's a there's a great overlap
between the test
mindset and asking what can go wrong
right do we do we account for all of
these weird conditions that we could
encounter
and the way in which we threat model and
think about security
so essentially the tests are there to
test for
the fact that our assumption is actually
true that
this control to that there should never
be any network connectivity
outbound on an unestablished connection
because that's associated with malware
so we're going to try to establish a
connection to an internet site somewhere
google dns or what have you if that
happens and succeeds then we should
immediately
fail the system and that's a broken test
so then
my follow-up is so then would these
live with your functional requirement
test suite or should this be
in its own special tests group for
security tests only
the more strat modeling influences
mainline development the happier i
am and let me just say on the on the
what to reach out to
a lot of companies have a server now
sitting in the cloud called break
glass and the test is
all of my machine information and i
connect to and then any time breakglass
gets a connection
that has the silly little password so it
doesn't get found by nmap scanning and
stuff
it breaks the glass the the place that
testing for security starts to look a
little different
is when you're doing penetration testing
if the way i'm going to address
sql injection is not prepared statements
then i need to have a whole suite of
specially designed
sql injection tests that are going to
find
these sorts of problems much better to
detect it early and say we're not going
to do dynamic sql
we're going to do prepared statements so
that the architecture manages this
threat
but if you do you need specialized tests
ideally those are in the mainline test
suite sometimes they'll also be broken
out in tagged security in some fashion
so you can run security specific tests
okay and then with these tests and all
these test cases who should actually be
right in them should it be the security
team a special person on the security
team
developers quality assurance qa
who should be doing this who writes your
tests
so essentially it should be the same
person that's writing your tests right
now for your test driven development
yes and sometimes that person is going
to get support from a security champ
a specialist on the security team but
the more we can infuse
look over the last decade or so
reliability has become a mainstream
concern
of software development
used to be we had a reliability and
scaling specialist function
and at a lot of places there are still
specialists
who can help with that and we expect our
developers to write reliable code
right they they need to come into the
room
with an understanding that their code is
going to be reliable
and oh by the way i've got this weird
issue that i don't know how to address
mr expert ms expert can you help me
figure out what to do in this scenario
but mainline
it is it is mainline it's the
responsibility of the person who's
building the system
okay so at the end of the day the
developer is responsible for actually
making sure that these things are
put in place because they're writing the
code therefore they should own the code
that they're putting out there
developers developers developers
developers
so switching gears a little bit here
let's move
into uh some of the tooling to keep
track of the overall threat modeling
process is there
any tooling that you would specifically
recommend a formal tooling excel
spreadsheets
a whiteboard a notepad a legal pad for
the lawyers
so i love threat modeling on a
whiteboard
i think it is the place where we get
the most organic highest value
and as you get into doing this
organizationally security teams often
want
structured data that they can run
analysis on they can run comparisons on
they want views into that this work is
being done they want the work to be
recorded in some way
so there's an o wasp tool called threat
dragon they just released version one
it's it's interesting i think there's a
lot of potential there
i'm on the advisory board of a company
called continuum
who have a system for doing threat
modeling across
hundreds of projects at scale as you
start out
i don't want you to start by selecting a
tool i want you to start out by
answering four questions
what are we working on what can go wrong
what are we going to do about it did we
do a good job
document that however works for you
over time requirements for the software
that you use
will come from where the pain points in
actually doing this work
what is the software going to do for me
gets you to a much
crisper answer than saying
what can software do for threat modeling
right do i go with dragon do i go with
continuum
you're not going to know the answer
until you've done
this a bunch of times so that you know
how it's going to work for you how it
integrates into your process
and delivers results for you and then
you can say how do we make this more
efficient
how do we make this more measurable how
do we improve the analysis that we're
performing
all of those software will help you with
as you develop maturity and skills in
threat modeling
exactly so it's almost that game gonna
need it concept don't
start by picking the tool out shelf that
concept for now
just do the threat modeling and then as
you start to get asked by stakeholders
for
well how many threats do you discover
when you take a new application and how
long does it take
on average to put these bugs into the
system
before they're assigned to a developer
and then a developer actually implements
the fix
and risk management is involved or
whatever metrics you want to track
against it
that's when you need to actually start
picking your tools and almost have that
feature set that you're looking for
based on those requirements
yes exactly all right so
just moving a little bit back towards
the start of the episode we kind of
discussed
why threat modeling is important so now
i kind of want to discuss how do i
take that threat model and why it's
important
and sell it to my organization how do i
sell it to my managers to say
i need time to work on threat modeling
this piece of software that we're
rolling out
in six months wow
we could we could do a whole episode on
this
let me let me start with the
structured approach to security
and the increased collaboration between
security and development
let me continue with
getting everyone out of whiteboard
discussing architecture
reduces rework if you get no security
benefit whatsoever and i've never seen
that happen from getting all the people
involved in a system in a room
drawing the system on a whiteboard and
arguing about how it works right there's
benefit
right there and
that benefit has payoff in lower rework
right it's not even a security benefit
but it gets you into the threat modeling
process
another thing that often comes up is i'm
tired of seeing the same pen test
results on every system
how do we get security earlier how do we
get this
moving in a way that's less difficult
for us
so those are all ways that help
organizations get
started and i'll plug a talk i did at
owasp
apsec california 2019 conference
put a link in the show notes but it's
entitled to seat at the table it's 30
minutes
on exactly this question awesome i'll
put a link to that in the show notes
definitely and i'll also put links to
those tools that you mentioned continuum
and the oauth threat dragon
but i know as a community we generally
like anecdotal stories to be able to you
know explain to management
well here's how this helped this
specific group can you
give us an example of a project where
threat modeling actually
discovered some type of severe
vulnerability that
you would have broken a build over if
you had known about it so this is one of
those questions that's really
tricky because for all of the good
problems that we find in
threat modeling many of them get fixed
and so the problem never
materializes many of the others
nobody wants to admit they knew that
could happen and decided it was too
difficult to fix
and so i have to go back a little ways
to come to a problem that's
really visible and for that i'm going to
talk about the zotob
worm and the zotob worm was one of these
fast spreading worms in the early 2000s
that really killed windows 2000
and was less bad against windows 2003
and the reason it was less bad in 2003
was because it had been discovered
threat modeling
the fix was really complicated
and so they put some mitigations into
that reduced the impact and when the bug
was externally discovered
there was no way to back port the fixes
to windows 2000 so it was
really severely impacted and i mentioned
this
in part because microsoft talks about
there's a fellow bob fruth who's talked
about it a lot he was in the room when
it happened
and so that's an example of
threat modeling actually dramatically
to use today's terminology flattening
the curve
of malware installation
because of threat modeling but a lot of
a lot of the
great proof points that i have are
great in the context of boy are we glad
we didn't ship that
and so i want to encourage people to
pilot
to go answer those four questions
quickly
and to use the discoveries that they're
making
as evidence for the organization to
adopt the practice
the bug in your code is way more
interesting than the bug in anyone
else's code
exactly so essentially sell to
management on the basis that
look even if this gives us no security
benefit
we at least will reduce rework we'll all
be on the same page
and by the way most likely we're gonna
find something really really bad and
you're all gonna be very happy that we
did this
yes and and you know getting started
five minutes of drawing on a whiteboard
using the elevation of privileged card
deck which we haven't talked about but
let me talk about
real briefly elevation appro and i want
people to suspend their disbelief for a
minute
elevation of privilege is a card game
that helps people threat model
and so it has cards and i'm just
grabbing a copy here
it has cards like the six of tampering
an attacker can write to a data store
your code relies on
so you draw a picture on the whiteboard
we say hey
what does this web server rely on here
are some configuration files and by the
way
i did not plan for the card i opened to
to be a threat that we had discussed
already on the show that was
that was a random little bit but the
game
it's freely downloadable if and we'll
put a link in the show notes it's
available for sale on amazon
it was designed as the easy way to get
started threat modeling
you can get started and get results
inside of an
hour i encourage you to do so okay where
would that fit in
is that between the diagramming process
and you know let's start using stride
is that where that card game would start
to get used so it
the the whiteboard diagram is what are
we working on
the card game the card game is built
around stride stride is a backbone for
the game
you don't need to know much about stride
to use it
and so it's a way of answering what are
we working on and what can go wrong
and because of the gamified nature of it
because of the hints on the cards
because the game gives people social
permission to be a little bit silly at
work
it encourages this free flow
of ideas perspectives
and so i have never
run a session where people have sat down
with the cards
and not gotten engaged inside of about
10 minutes
and i'm very hands-off you don't need me
in the room exactly so i'll definitely
put a link to the show notes
for the card deck and i believe there's
instructions that come with that as well
for how to run the game there are yes
awesome
so one last kind of topic switch here
before
we start to wrap up the threat modeling
of new software
does it change at all for you know web
api driven software
the internet of things or whatever the
latest term for that
concept of embedded systems everywhere
is or you know containerized services
running docker
or some other kubernetes cluster
executing docker under the hood
yes it does change right the answer to
what are we working on
the answers to what can go wrong the
answers to what are we going to do about
it are different in each of these
for example in iot
there's often a concern about if people
change the passwords how do they get
back into
the device and so you have to think
about that
the the thing that remains the same
across all of these
is the four question framework and
there's a trap
in what you're asking which is totally
natural
people say how do i threat model this
particular thing
just get started dive in and threat
model
do an analysis don't worry about the
specifics
i mean when i say don't worry about the
specifics don't worry about the
specifics of what your threat modeling
and the way
that threat modeling affects
microservices or web driven apis
build a threat model as you develop
skill
you will realize that the threats to the
web api
tend to be like this the threats to iot
tend to be like this but if i were to
try to give
advice for each of these specific things
right how do we apply the four questions
in this specific thing that i'm working
on
we end up with this explosion of
variance right
how do i threat model lambda services
written in go that are offering web apis
okay it's a valid question we threat
model it with the four questions
and the way we answer what can go wrong
and what are we going to do about it
is different in that scenario than it is
if my web api is written in i don't know
pearl
right a lot more is going to go wrong
with pearl frankly and i say that as a
as a fan of the language but we've
learned a lot since it was created
exactly so really don't worry about what
technology you're implementing this with
just do the actual threat modeling and
while you may not have as many you know
specific types of threats with a web api
and iot device on the other hand you're
going to be worried a lot about physical
access threats whereas
your web api sitting in aws probably not
as much about some type of physical
mechanism that you're going to attack it
with
yes and when when we're talking about
iot and physical access
people often say oh that's in the home
it's no big deal
think about think about people who use
airbnb
people who install this in their store
or other open area
think about the house cleaner and so
there's often a desire to
scope this and say oh it's in someone's
home it's an iot device
it's safe when you think about what can
go wrong with a little bit more
structure you realize that there are
answers to that question
which don't let you dismiss this and say
all the threats are necessarily out of
scope
or maybe you put a label on the box that
says not appropriate for airbnb
rented properties right a little bit of
a warning label going back to your
question about
what do we tell the end user what do we
tell the buyer
exactly i have to stick the label on the
box that says do not allow
unfettered physical access to this
device as it may result in
negative consequences for you or from
the company perspective
take my threat model and say you know
what even the end consumer
i'm going to assume might be evil
because this is eventually connecting to
my api in the back end
so from that perspective they're an
external entity the whole device is an
external entity connecting to my api
so my trust boundaries between my api
and the device
yes trusting trusting a device that sits
in
the hands of an end user for extended
periods of time
is well let me just say that when i do
attack work it's a lot of fun
so i just want to kind of uh close out
the episode a little bit here
is there anything that i miss that you
think developers and software engineers
should know
i think that the the biggest thing i
want to emphasize
is that threat modeling is a big
collection of techniques that can look
very intimidating when you get started
there are four simple questions what are
we working on
what can go wrong what are we going to
do about it and did we do a good job
if you ask those questions if you treat
the last question did we do a good job
as not just a mechanical question of did
we find some threats do we have a
diagram
but also as an opportunity to do
retrospectives
as you're starting this work to say what
went well what went poorly what do we
keep what do we change
and in fact i tell people to start out
with a one-to-one ratio of time spent
threat modeling
and time doing retrospectives that falls
off very quickly but that early
listening really helps organizations
start to threat model and do it in a way
that brings them value
fantastic and then are you doing any
further in-depth research on the topic
of threat modeling i am so i've been
thinking a lot
about conflict about
abuse of user-generated content
trolling deep fakes
abuse that happens online and so i've
been thinking about that
i'm talking to a team at oxford
university
who's bringing the techniques of threat
modeling to
intimate partner violence how do we use
these techniques to shed a light on the
way in which technology
intersects with that form of abuse and
the unique ways that it happens
i'm doing research into art can we
create
additional taxonomies around things like
fraud that more and more organizations
are using
and i'm keeping i'm also keeping my eyes
on things like machine learning
what what is new and different about
threat modeling
in iot and to me these are fascinating
questions
these are how do we build new tools in
that toolbox
but we can achieve good value without
those tools we'll achieve
more value with them that's fantastic
and where can listeners
follow your research and all these
things that you're
you know trying to push out into the
community to increase knowledge on
threat modeling
so the best way is adam.stack
blog and i try and keep that
a little more focused than an old school
blog i try for
posts that are on topic that are a
little bit more in-depth
so that would be the the number one
place to go
there's also i want to mention a great
resource
the owasp slack community has a really
active threat modeling channel we've got
about a thousand people in it we have
lots of interesting discussions ranging
from the very broad to the very specific
so join in and
it's a great way to meet other people
who are struggling with similar problems
to what you have
that's fantastic i'll definitely put
links to both of those in the show notes
that way it's easier for people to find
so adam i just want to close out the
episode and thank you for coming on the
show to discuss threat modeling
techniques and how we can apply them to
our software development processes
thank you this has been a lot of fun
this is justin baier for software
engineering radio
thank you for listening developers take
your marks
it's time to upgrade your data platform
to inner systems iris
it's time to deliver complex mission
critical applications in the fastest
route possible
it's time to use any data from any
source it's time to embed analytics and
create interactive user interfaces
so what are you waiting for choose your
language choose your tools
choose your environment collaborate
build faster
and deploy more efficiently done and
done tomorrow's next breakthroughs are
waiting for you today
intersystems iris data platform the
fastest way to build applications
ready set code start coding for free
visit intersystems.com try to try iris
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine
for more about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at se
radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on linkedin
facebook twitter or through our slack
channel at
scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of sc radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening